Guide to the Robert Livingston papers 1974.018
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 2: Five Nations Documents
  - Propositions made by Sachems of Cagnawaga / Kahnawake, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    Propositions made by Sachems of Cagnawaga / Kahnawake [Quebec Mohawk] to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs at Albany, Robert Livingston, 28 January 1700, with reply, a draft ("This is corrected & transcribed") [20th c. note, in pencil: "original draft {Compare "Colonial History of New York", Vol. IV p. 692, for the "corrected" copy.}"].
  - Propositions to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs at Albany, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    (3 items) Indian Propositions to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs at Albany, Robert Livingston, et al., being two drafts dated 30 June 1700 and one dated 3 July 1700 (with the Commissioners reply), re: relations between the Five Nations, the French government of Canada, and various Canadian tribes, including the Dowaganhaes [the Iriquois name for the Ottowa (and possibly also the Chippewa or Ojibwa), alternately spelled Dowanganhaes, Dowaganhas, or Waganhaes]; the drafts mention colonial administrators Peter Schuyler, Peter Van Brugh, Jan Janse Bleecker, Johannes Schuyler, David Schuyler, Johannes Rooseboom, Evert Wendell, Wessell Ten Broeck, and Thomas Williams, and various Indian sachems [each draft with 20th c. note, in pencil, referring to the Colonial History of New York, Vol. IV: 1. "See p.693 … a first draft;" 2. "p.693… the corrected draft;" 3. "the original draft … p. 695"].
  - "Our answer to the Praying Indians (of Canada) and their Reply", 1700 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Unsigned document, titled "Our answer to the Praying Indians (of Canada) and their Reply," Albany, 3 July 1700 [20th c. note, in pencil: "original draft, Col. Hist. N. Y., IV, p. 692"].
  - Minutes of a conference between the Earl of Bellomont and four Indian sachems, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Minutes of a Conference between the Earl of Bellomont and four Indian sachems - Kanogari and Orachqui of the Senecas, and Aquiendero alias Sadskanakti and Kashewagyiris of the Onondagas, Albany, 19 August 1700 [20th c. note, in pencil: "not in Col. Hist, Vol. IV"], mentions witnesses Peter Schuyler, Abraham de Peyster, Jan Janse Bleecker, Ryer Schermerhorn, and Hendrick Hanse.
  - Accounts of conferences between the Earl of Bellomont and sachems of the Five Nations, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    (3 items) Accounts of conferences between the Earl of Bellomont and sachems of the Five Nations, at Albany: a copy in Dutch dated 26 August 1700, an English translation of the same date, and an English version of the conference dated 28 August 1700, all re: conversion of the Indians to Christianity, noting the attempts of the Jesuits of French Canada to "deceive and seduce" the Indians from obedience to the King of England, and promising the delivery of Protestant ministers to preach among the Indians in their own language; the Dutch copy contains extensive lists of the colonial witnesses and of the sachems by tribe [CG] [20th c. remarks in pencil note that the English translation of the 26 August conference appears on pages 727-8 of the Colonial History of New York, Vol. IV, and that the 28 August conference appears on page 732].
  - Propositions made by six chiefs of the Magnase (Mohawk) Protestant Indians to Richard, the Earl of Bellomont, at Albany, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    Propositions made by six chiefs of the Magnase (Mohawk) Protestant Indians to Richard, the Earl of Bellomont, at Albany, 26 August 1700, with the Earl's reply, re: Christian instruction of the Indians, mentions Mr. Freeman [20th c. note in pencil: see Col. Hist. N.Y. Vol. IV, p. 727].
  - Proposal of Henry of the Magnase (Mohawks) to the Earl of Bellomont, at Albany, 1700 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Proposal of Henry of the Magnase (Mohawks) to the Earl of Bellomont, at Albany, 31 August 1700, offering beaver skins and praying "that ye Great King of England may protect us from any harm that may befall us" [20th c. note in pencil: Col. Hist. N.Y. Vol. IV, p. 743].
  - "True copy of Peter Schuyler & Robert Livingston in answer upon ye Commisssioners Memoriall", 1701 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    "True copy of Peter Schuyler & Robert Livingston in answer upon ye Commisssioners Memoriall", 4 April 1701, re: a message delivered 29 March 1701 to the President and members of His Majesty's council for the Province of New York, following the death of Richard, Earl of Bellomont [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Journal of a trip to Canada, 1702 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    Journal of a trip to Canada and back, made by David Schuyler, Wessel Ten Broeck, and Jean Rosie [Johannes Roseboom?], 5 September 1702 [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Journal of John Baptist van Eps and Laurence Claese and a message from the Sachems of the Onondaga, 1702 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    (2 items) Two documents, re: French Jesuit Priests from Canada found in Onondaga country: the Journal of John Baptist van Eps and Laurence Claese of their trip to Onondaga on behalf of Colonel Peter Schuyler, and, a message from the Sachems of the Onondaga, both dated Albany, 8 November 1702.
  - Copy of a letter to Lord Cornbury, 1702 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    An early copy of a letter to Lord Cornbury, from Robert Livingston, re: the preceding items (see folder # 52), indicating that John van Eps is returning to Onondaga, with a belt of wampum and a message that his Lordship "will not approove of [the Onondaga's] Receiving Jesuits into their Country" [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Proposals to the Five Nations, Albany, 1703 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    Proposals to the Five Nations, Albany, 1703, in Dutch, re: replies to proposals made by the Indians the previous day: Peace has been made between England and France, so the Five Nations should no longer kill the French; the Jesuits are deceitful, not to be believed; Mohawks request news about events in Europe [CG] [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Account, taken from 3 sachems of Schaahkook [ Schachtekook ], at Albany, 1703 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Account, taken from 3 sachems of Schaahkook [ Schachtekook ], at Albany, 26 June 1703, re: the killing of a frenchman at Quachkeek near Pennekook by "some English," and of the scalping of an englishman and the taking of 3 prisoners by "3 french and 2 Indians from Canada," the document witnessed by Peter Schuyler, Dirck Wessels, Evert Bancker, and Albert Ryckman, with accounting of presents [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Propositions and replies, between sachems of the Mohawk, Oneida, Onondaga and Cayuga, and the Commissioners at Albany, 1703 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    Propositions and replies, between sachems of the Mohawk, Oneida, Onondaga and Cayuga, and the Commissioners at Albany, made the 22nd, 23rd, 24th and 29th July 1703, all on one sheet, re: comments made by the Jesuits to the Indians concerning the intentions of the English Crown, the Commissioners insisting on the falsehood of such reports, and also a Mohawk request for assistance in building a fort at Tionnonderoga [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - "Examination of an Indian called Cayingquiragoe, come here from Canada", 1703 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    "Examination of an Indian called Cayingquiragoe, come here from Canada", Albany, 29 September 1703, re: French scouts "on ye River of Chamly" [Lake Champlain?], Canada Indians prepared for war against New England, Ottowawa Indians at Montréal, and the Governor of Canada on a mission to Québec [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Propositions made by Brant and one other Mohawk sachem, 1703 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    Propositions made by Brant and one other Mohawk sachem, Albany, 26 October 1703, giving account of how the French and their Indian allies "persuaded ye Indians of two Castles of Onnagongwee" [Onondaga?] to fight with them against New Englanders, resulting in the killing of 180 of the latter [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Intelligence from Onondaga, 1704 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Intelligence from Onondaga, re: talks with Canada, together with the draft of a complaint by Robert Livingston against Philip Phillipse of Schenectady, for debts unpaid, all one sheet [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. IV, Col Hist. N.Y."].
  - Warrant from Queen Anne, 1705 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    Warrant, from Queen Anne, 12 December 1705, authorising payment by high treasurer Sidney Lord Godolphin to Robert Livingston, for his assistance to two companies of foot at New York, those of Captain James Weems and Colonel Ingoldsby, the warrant addressed to Richard Earl of Ranelagh and entered by William Blaithwayt, an early copy, signed as received by Livingston (initials).
  - Complaint of abuses in New England, 1707 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    Complaint of abuses in New England, by Henry and by Brant Jacob, Mohawk Indians, made to the Commissioners of Indian Affairs at Albany, 9 May 1707, signed by Philip Livingston, Deputy Secretary [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - News from the sachems at Onondaga, 1708 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    News from the sachems at Onondaga relayed by Laurence Claese the interpreter, re: the French building of two forts for garrisons to be posted at Sweegasie and Oghjagre on hunting territory of the Five Nations, of the colonial government's late neglect of its covenant with the Five Nations, of attempts by the French to gain favor among the Onondaga, of Oneidas gone to visit Canada, of Canadian Indians hunting on the grounds of the Five Nations, threats of war against New England, etc. [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Translation of a report from Onondaga, 1709 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    Translation of a report from Onondaga, a copy sent to Lord Cornbury, March 1709, relating difficulties in the affairs of the Five Nations, the colonial government, Canada and Canadian Indians, mentions Indian sachems by name [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - "Information given by Laurence Claese, interpreter, relating affairs at Onondaga", 1704 (Box 1, Folder 64)
    "Information given by Laurence Claese, interpreter, relating affairs at Onondaga," at Albany, 2 June 1704, and "Propositions given by two sachems of Mohogs (Mohawk) Castle," at Albany, 3 June 1704, both on one sheet; Claese reports of a visit to the Onondaga by a Monsieur Longuel from Canada, and of what Longuel is telling them; the Mohawk sachems inform the Albany government of exchanged visits between their people and the Cagnawages (Kahnawake) of Canada, and relate Colonel Schuyler's reply [The dating of this letter may be questioned – it was previously thought to be "1709"; 20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."
  - Two letters from Colonel Peter Schuyler and a letter addressed "May it please your Excellency", 1709 (Box 1, Folder 65)
    (3 items) Three letters, unsigned, being early copies: Two letters from Colonel Peter Schuyler, at Albany, to William Whiting of Westfield, MA, 7 June 1709, re: intelligence of threats to New England made by the governor of Montréal, and requesting that New Englanders refrain from encouraging deserters from the garrison at Albany; also, a letter addressed "May it please your Excellency," re: messengers from William Whiting of Westfield, and of a reply to Whiting that there is "no certainty of a settlement - but that … if a settlement be made it must be upon a River called Quaasick which runs towards New England" [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Proposition made by Toquajnoui, 1709 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    Proposition made by Toquajnoui [sp?] at Albany, 10 June 1709, with answer, and a resolution made at Albany, 20 June 1709, all on one sheet: Toquajnoui requests that his relations, who have been scattered by divisions within the "praying Indians of Canawage Castle in Canada" created by "this war," be permitted to settle with him, and his request is accepted; and the commissioners of Indian Affairs and Albany aldermen resolve that a Christian be sent out with these Indians as a scout [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Scouts account, Proposition made by Wallaglawit a Sachem, and Instructions, 1709 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    "Information given by Captain Johannes Bratt & Elbert Harmense who were sent out Skouts with 7 Indians towards ye Lake, now come home," Albany, 23 June 1709, with "Proposition made by Wallaglawit a Sachem of ye Shaahkook Indians," et al., Albany, 24 June 1709, and Answer, also, "Instructions for Hendrick Vroman [or Vrooman] and Cornelis Hendrickse with 2 Indians," 24 June 1709, all on one sheet: the scouts's account seemingly a fragment of a mission to Saratoga and beyond; Wallaglawit's proposition: "Father Corlaer – It is many years a-gone when we were a great nation and of great number. Then we called one [an]other Brethren, but since we are become a few people we call you father and therefore Truly Resolved to live and die with you …" re: the difficulties of his people in finding beaver to hunt and land to plant corn, answered sympathetically; Vroman and Hendrickse instructed to march north, beyond Saratoga, to "Lake St. Sacrament," to spy on "enemy" and return to Schenectady [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Draft of a cover letter from Colonel Schuyler, 1709 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    Draft of a cover letter, from Colonel Schuyler, at Albany, to Lord Cornbury, at New York, 19 August 1709, unsigned, re: enclosing an account of the Colonel's journey to the Four Nations, requesting payment for costs of the same and for provisions [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - "Proposals made by the Sachems of the Five Nations to his Excellency Robert Hunter, Captain General & Governor in Chief, etc.,", 1711 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    "Proposals made by the Sachems of the Five Nations to his Excellency Robert Hunter, Captain General & Governor in Chief, etc.," Albany, 26 August 1711, re: giving thanks for materials with which to build forts, and requesting that Robert Livingston's salary be paid, includes list of witnesses and interpreters and gives definitions: "Brother Corlaer – the Indian name of the Governors of New York; Annadagarriax – the Indian name of Lieut. General Fr. Nicholson" [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Letter, from Governor Robert Hunter, 1713 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    Letter, from Governor Robert Hunter, at New York, to the Commissioners of Indian Affairs, at Albany, 8 May 1713, re: the redemption of an Indian of the Five Nations captured among the Tuscaroras of North Carolina, with instructions to the Commissioners to restrain the Five Nations from joining with the Tuscaroras at war with the Carolinians, "her Majesty's subjects" [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Propositions made by Blew Bek, chief of the Senecas, and Dekanissore [a.k.a, Decanesora / Teganissorens ], chief of the Onondaga, 1713 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    Propositions made by Blew Bek, chief of the Senecas, and Dekanissore [a.k.a, Decanesora / Teganissorens ], chief of the Onondaga, et al., to the Commissioners of Indian Affairs at Albany, 2 and 3 June 1713, with replies, on 4 separate sheets [extensive, and barely legible], re: diverse topics, including matters of war, relations with the colonial government, problems with "strong Drink," mentions the Tuscarora and Catawba ("Flathead") tribes of the Carolinas, and the Dowaganhaes (Ottawa) of Canada; Dekanissore indicates he is inclined to resign as Sachem.
  - Five Nations response to William Burnet, 1722 (Box 1, Folder 72)
    "Answer made by the Five Nations of Indians, viz. the Magnase, Oneydes, Onnondages, Cayouges & Sinnekes, to his Excellency William Burnet, Esq., Capt. Generall and Govern. In Chief of the Provinces of New York, New Jersey, and Territories thereon Depending and vice admirall of the same," Albany, 1st and 4th September 1722, "interpreted by Laurence Claese in Dutch and rendered into English by Robert Livingston" (those present: William Burnet, Rip van Dam, John Barbarie, Dr. Cadwallader Colden, James Alexander, Col. Lewis Morris Jr., Peter van Brugh, Johannes Cuyler, Evert Bancker, Philip Livingston, Johannes Wendell), on 5 pages sewn together, re: promises made not to correspond with the French of Canada, encouragement of "the farr Indians" to come trade at Albany, the Governor's orders "not to go a-fighting towards Virginia," communications with the Governor, a resolution to discourage and not to join warring French Indians, a rejection of overtures by the Tuscarora to make war on the Todirighgroones [of Virginia], a conference between sachems (including Blewbeck of the Seneca) and the Governor of Canada, war with the Flatheads, loyalty to the English, mentions presence of Governor Alexander Spotswood of Virginia and Governor William Keith of Pennsylvania [20th c. note in pencil: "in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y., p. 658-666"].
  - Letter from the Commissioners of Indian Affairs William Burnet, 1723 (Box 1, Folder 73)
    Letter, from the Comissioners of Indian Affairs, at Albany, to Governor William Burnet, 29 October 1723, an early copy, the original signed by Henry Holland, Johannes Cuyler, Evert Bancker, Philip Livingston, John Collins, Johannes Bleecker, Evert Wendell (Cornelis Cuyler absent), re: expressing strong concerns for the safety of Albany in light of recent attacks by Indians from Canada at Northfield, near Rutland, in their war with New England, blaming the actions of Colonel John Schuyler for the Colony's peril, noting also that the "Far Indians" will not trade with the Colony in time of war, mentions a mission by Philip Schuyler and John Groesbeek to Canada to redeem captives [20th c. note in pencil: "not in Vol. V, Col. Hist. N.Y."].
  - Agreement made with Paulus Dik, 1725 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    Agreement made with Paulus Dik concerning land in Livingston Manor sold by Robert Livingston in 1710, dated 1 July 1725, in Dutch [CG].
  - Processing note (Box 1, Folder 75)
    Processing note on envelope, unknown origin,"Miscellaneous 1753-1800."
  - Proclamation by Governor George Clinton, 1753 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    Proclamation, given by Governor George Clinton of the Province of New York, ordering the arrests of inhabitants of Massachusetts Bay and New Hampshire Josiah Loomis, William Webb, John Hallenbeck (son of Michael Hallenbeck), Joseph Arcourt, Jonathan Younglove, David Picksley, et al. – for encroachments upon lands in Albany and Dutchess counties in the Province of New York and the abduction of Robert Vanduersen and his son, Johannes Vanduersen, from Livingston Manor on 19 July 1753, printed matter.
  - Copy of a Land Deed, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    Copy of a Land Deed by which "the Insurgents first founded their claims," the original signed on 15 March 1757, conveying land from two Indian proprietors Benjamin Kaukewenuhonaunt, sachem, and Mankuwarent [var. spelling], hunter, both of Stockbridge, Hampshire county, Massachusetts Bay province - to John Hallenbeck, William Hallenbeck, et al., 81 purchasers listed in all (compare names with those in the above Proclamation, Livingston Papers, folder # 76), the land said to lie within Hampshire county, nine witnesses listed, approved by Justice Timothy Woodbridge, recorded on 7 April 1762, and the copy made by Caleb Hyde Jr., dated at Lenox, 17 September 1792.